Jeanne Penvenne Papers MS238
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Jeanne Penvenne Papers
circa 1995 -- 2018
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Penvenne, Jeanne
MS238
1.6 Linear Feet
This collection contains the papers of Jeanne Penvenne, professor in the Tufts University Department of History from 1993-2018, including material by or about her colleague Gerald R. Gill (1948-2007).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. Please contact DCA for further details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeanne Penvenne, 2017-2018.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series: Jeanne Penvenne Papers on Gerald R. Gill; and 2018 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
Gerald R. Gill (1948-2007) taught American history at Tufts University from 1980-2007. He began as an assistant professor, served as an associate professor beginning in 1987, and became the history department's deputy chair in 1998. He was a leading scholar in the field of African-American history and the history of the civil rights movement. He was also a founding and core member of several interdisciplinary programs at Tufts, including American Studies, Africa in the New World Studies, and Peace and Justice Studies. Gill was born on November 18, 1948 in New Rochelle, New York, to Robert and Etta Gill. He received a bachelor's degree in history in 1970 from Lafayette College, where he was one of the founders of Lafayette's Association of Black Collegians and the Black Cultural Center. He then earned a master's degree in United States history (1974) and a doctorate in history (1985) from Howard University in Washington D.C. A conscientious objector during the Vietnam War, Gill wrote his dissertation on the history of twentieth-century African-American pacifism. Gill taught at Howard University (1975-1978), University of the District of Columbia (1978), Harvard University (1979), and UCLA (1986), in addition to Tufts University (1980-2007). He received a number of teaching awards and honors, including Professor of the Year for Massachusetts (twice, in 1995 and 1999); the Lerman-Neubauer Prize for Outstanding Teaching and Advising (1998); the Tufts Community Union Senate's Professor of the Year Award (1999); and the Lillian and Joseph Leibner Award for Distinguished Teaching and Advising (1993). The Distinguished Service Award for Outstanding Contributions to the Tufts Community, bestowed on Gill in 2000 by the university's Africana Center, was renamed the Gerald R. Gill Distinguished Service Award in his honor the same year. He was also awarded research fellowships at the W.E.B. Dubois Institute at Harvard (1979), the Center for Afro-American Studies at U.C.L.A. (1985), and a National Endowment for the Humanities fellowship at the Schomberg Center for Research in Black Culture (1997). Gill's university service included membership on many committees, particularly those related to undergraduate education and advising. In addition to teaching, mentoring students, and writing, Gill served as a consultant on many public television and documentary projects, including Eyes on the Prize, The American Experience, Africans in America, This Far by Faith, and I'll Make Me a World. He was the author of Meanness Mania: The Changed Mood (1980), co-authored The Case for Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education (1978), edited the Faculty Guide and Student Study Guide for the Eyes on the Prize (1991), and co-edited The Eyes on the Prize Civil Rights Reader (1991). At the time of his death, he was working on two unpublished books: Struggling Yet in Freedom's Birthplace: The Civil Rights Movement in Boston, 1935-1972, a history of Boston race relations; and Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States War of the Twentieth Century, an extension of his doctoral dissertation. Gill was divorced with one daughter, Ayanna Gill. He died in Cambridge, Massachusetts, on July 26, 2007.
Related Materials
Gerald R. Gill Papers, 1921-2007. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains material by or about Gerald R. Gill kept by Jeanne Penvenne, his colleague in the History Department, including correspondence, articles and publications, press clippings, photographs, Gill's obituary and various remembrances, and other memorabilia. This collection also contains office files, including correspondence, meeting notes, fliers, and other materials documenting the Black Cultural Studies Seminar, the Africana Film Festival, the Kenya Program, the Africa and the New World Program, the Gill Fellows Program, and the Senior Honors Thesis Exchange; video cassettes of the 2003 World Food Day Conference and the 2004 LUCE Seminar at Tufts; as well as a sample of student work on which Penvenne either served as advisor or reader, including senior theses and Gerald Gill Prize-nominated papers.
Biographical / Historical
Jeanne Marie Penvenne was born in Pittsfield, Massachusetts in 1947. From 1993 through 2018, she was a professor in the Tufts University Department of History, specializing in the history of labor conditions in Mozambique. She is married to Norman Robert Bennett, and together they have two children and four grandchildren.
Penvenne earned an Associate's Degree from Berkshire Community College in 1967, a B.A. in History and Philosophy from Northeastern University in 1972, and Ph.D. in History from Boston University in 1982. Between her B.A. and Ph.D. degrees, Penvenne joined the Peace Corps and was stationed in Brazil, where she learned Portuguese. With her knowledge of the language, Penvenne focused her dissertation research on the labor history of Mozambique. She has published widely on this topic, including her first book, African Workers and Colonial Racism; Mozambican Strategies for Survival in Lourenço Marques, Mozambique 1877-1962 (1995), as well as Women, Migration and the Cashew Economy of Southern Mozambique, 1945 to 1975 (2015), a study of the cashew women's economic, social, and urban histories.
After teaching at Boston University, Penvenne was appointed Assistant Professor in the Tufts University History Department in 1993, was tenured and promoted to Associate Professor in 1997, and became Full Professor in 2016. Penvenne was also involved in other departments at Tufts, including International Relations and Political Science, in which she served as thesis reader for numerous students and helped establish the Thesis Exchange, a space for thesis writers in various departments to share ideas and problems. Penvenne was recognized for her teaching and service at Tufts with the Lerman Neubauer Prize for Outstanding Teaching and Advising (1999), the Lillian and Joseph Leibner Award for Excellence in Teaching and Advising (2001), and the Seymour Simches Award for Distinguished Teaching and Advising (2018), among others. She has also received awards for her scholarly work from the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Mellon Foundation, and the U.S. Public Affairs Office.
After the unexpected death in 2007 of Gerald Gill, her friend and colleague in the History Department, Penvenne worked closely with the Gill family to bring his papers to the Tufts Digital Collections and Archives. The collection was donated in 2017. In 2018, Penvenne retired and became Professor of History, Emerita.
Tufts University -- Faculty -- Archives.; Faculty papers; Tufts University. Department of History.; Gill, Gerald R.
- Jeanne Penvenne papers on Gerald R. Gill, circa 1995 -- 2007; MS238.001; 13 Folder(s)
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Jeanne Penvenne, 2017, accession MS-2018-010.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material by or about Gerald Gill kept by Jeanne Penvenne, his colleague in the History Department, including correspondence, articles and publications, press clippings, photographs, and other memorabilia. This series also includes Gill's obituary and various remembrances.
  - Articles and publications, circa 1997 -- 2007; MS238.001.001.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Schomburg Scholarship, 1997 -- 1998; MS238.001.001.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - History Department photographs, circa 1997 -- 2007; MS238.001.001.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Obituary and remembrances, 2007; MS238.001.001.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Press clippings, circa 1997 -- 2007; MS238.001.001.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Carnegie MA Professor of the Year photographs, 1995; MS238.001.001.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Tufts graduations photographs, circa 1997 -- 2007; MS238.001.001.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Reference, 2006; MS238.001.001.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Billy Ruth Perryman textile, circa 1997 -- 2007; MS238.001.001.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Alumni weekend, 2007; MS238.001.001.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - JFK Library and Museum, 1998; MS238.001.001.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - "Another Limit", circa 1997 -- 2007; MS238.001.001.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
  - Poetry, circa 1997 -- 2007; MS238.001.001.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_65a71f1b586eb2b14bcecedb8e01bd80, Box 1)
- 2018 accessions, circa 1997 -- 2018; MS238.002; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. Please contact DCA for further details.
  Gift of Jeanne Penvenne, 2018, accession MS-2019-003.
  This series is arranged in received order, and retains original folder titles.
  This series contains office files, including correspondence, meeting notes, fliers, and other materials documenting the Black Cultural Studies Seminar, the Africana Film Festival, the Kenya Program, the Africa and the New World Program, the Gill Fellows Program, and the Senior Honors Thesis Exchange. This series also contains video cassettes of the 2003 World Food Day Conference and the 2004 LUCE Seminar at Tufts, Penvenne's correspondence with Gerald Gill's daughter Ayanna Gill, as well as a sample of student work on which Penvenne either served as advisor or reader, including senior theses and Gerald Gill Prize-nominated papers.
  - Black cultural studies seminars, 1997 -- 1998; MS238.002.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 1, Box 2)
    Open for research.
  - Black cultural studies seminar, 1998 -- 1999; MS238.002.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 2, Box 2)
  - Black cultural studies, 1999 -- 2000; MS238.002.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 3, Box 2)
  - Black cultural studies seminar, 1999 -- 2000; MS238.002.002.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 4, Box 2)
  - Black cultural studies seminar, Sharpe/Coleman, 2001; MS238.002.002.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 5, Box 2)
  - Black cultural studies seminar archival posters, 1997 -- 2000; MS238.002.002.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 6, Box 2)
  - Africa and the new world program, 2002 -- 2003; MS238.002.002.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 7, Box 2)
  - Field, Kendra Gerald Gill fellow applications, 2016 -- 2017; MS238.002.002.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 8, Box 2)
  - Rachel Brown Kenya program, 2010; MS238.002.002.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 9, Box 2)
  - Africana film festival, 2001; MS238.002.002.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 10, Box 2)
  - Senior honors thesis exchange flyers, 2010 -- 2018; MS238.002.002.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 11, Box 2)
  - Ayanna Gill, 2015 -- 2017; MS238.002.002.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 12, Box 2)
    75 years from date of creation.
  - Gerald Gill prize papers, circa 2012; MS238.002.002.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 13, Box 2)
  - "A Rock in a Mine Field: Black Women's Life Strategies in Modern South Africa" Sarah Gene Byala, 1997; MS238.002.002.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 14, Box 2)
  - Farming in Africa- Bailis course pack, 1998; MS238.002.002.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 15, Box 2)
  - "Malaria in Ghanaian Children: A Historical Analysis from Independence to Present" Jocelyn Vitale, 1998; MS238.002.002.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 16, Box 2)
  - "The Power and Politics of Sexuality in Louis XVI's Scheme of Absolute Sovereignty: The Socio-Political Role of the Mistress in the Court of Louis XVI, 1661-1682" Julie R. Foster, 2007; MS238.002.002.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 17, Box 2)
  - "The Bulwark of Liberty: Oak and the Royal Navy" Michael Siegfried, 2007; MS238.002.002.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 18, Box 2)
  - "Citizens by Choice: Patterns of Urban Citizenship Acquisition 1900-1945" Philip J. Moss, 2007; MS238.002.002.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 19, Box 2)
  - "Sustainable Development through Microcredit and Socio-Ecological Resilience in Madagascar" Amanda L. Fencl, 2007; MS238.002.002.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 20, Box 2)
  - "A Handbook for Working with Battered Chinese Women" Patty Wu, 1998; MS238.002.002.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 21, Box 2)
  - "Africa Inside Me" Hassantu Blake, 2004; MS238.002.002.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 22, Box 2)
  - "China and Angola: A Transformative Relationship" Tessa Henry, 2010; MS238.002.002.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 23, Box 2)
  - "Engineering Peace: A Ugandan Civil Society Organization's Role in the Juba Peace Process" Laura Zachary 2009, MS238.002.002.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 24, Box 2)
  - "Stronger than the Hippocratic Oath: HIV and Hunger in a State of Denial" Sarah Carpenter, 2012; MS238.002.002.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 25, Box 2)
  - "The Effectiveness of Ghana's Structural Adjustment Policies After 1983" Leanna Byerlee, 1995; MS238.002.002.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Folder 26, Box 2)
  - World food day teleconference, 2003; MS238.002.002.00027; 1 Video Recordings (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Object 27, Box 2)
  - LUCE seminars: curriculum co-development with African universities, 2004; MS238.002.002.00028; 1 Video Recordings (Box data_value_missing_9d96a240e9e0b92d67a366dfc9d2fb98, Object 28, Box 2)